<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC 
	"-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<book>

<bookinfo>
	<title>IETest</title>
	<copyright>
		<year>2005</year>
		<holder>BestBrains ApS</holder>
	</copyright>

<keywordset>
	<keyword>IETest</keyword>
	<keyword>Internet Explorer</keyword>
	<keyword>Test</keyword>
	<keyword>Test Driven Development</keyword>
	<keyword>NUnit</keyword>
</keywordset>
</bookinfo>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[of]:Introduction-->
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[of]: - License-->
<!--[c](Denne sektion er udkommenteret ind til videre...)-->
<!--[c]-->
<!--[c]<section>-->
<!--[c]<title>License</title>-->
<!--[c]<para>-->
<!--[c]Bablah.. -->
<!--[c]</para>-->
<!--[c]</section>-->
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - What is IETest?-->
<section>
<title>What is IETest?</title>
<para>
IETest is a .NET library for testing web sites through Microsoft Internet Explorer.
It enables you to automate Internet Explorer to the point where you can perform automated testing without any human attention required.
</para>
<para>
IETest is developed by <ulink url="http://www.bestbrains.dk">BestBrains Aps</ulink>, a Danish software development consultancy 
company specializing in agile methods and test driven development. 
It is open source, released under the <ulink url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.php">MIT license</ulink> and hosted
on <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ietest"><graphic fileref="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=138358&amp;type=5"></graphic></ulink>
</para>
<para>
Other frameworks supply similar functionality: <ulink url="http://wtr.rubyforge.org/">Watir</ulink> which is Ruby based, and <ulink url="http://ieunit.sourceforge.net/">IeUnit</ulink> which is JavaScript based.
IETest is .NET based and supports modeless dialogs.
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - Download-->
<section>
<title>Download</title>
<para>
You can download the latest source code here: <ulink url="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/ietest/ietest-0.2.zip?download">ietest-0.2.zip</ulink>.
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - About TDD-->
<section>
<title>About Test Driven Development</title>
<para>
Test driven development is a very efficient way of developing code. It is gaining popularity and test tools are ever improving. Automated testing
of UI code seems to lack behind a little, though. With good reason - simulating a user is tedious and error prone. 
Using IETest, testing your ui becomes possible. Like with all software, writing tests for your web applications has a way of automatically making you 
write better code.
You will be more likely to give elements unique and intuitive identifiers and less likely to write hacks that might well work but would be difficult to test.
For a thorough discussion about the wonders and challenges of test driven development, take a look at 
<ulink url="http://www.testdriven.com">Testdriven.com</ulink>.
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[c]-->
</section>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]:Getting started-->
<section>
<title>Getting Started</title>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[of]: - Prerequisites and installation, NUnit..-->
<section>
<title>Installation and Prerequisites</title>
<para>
IETest requires the .NET framework version 1.1 or later.
IETest is built with C#. So far, it has only been used with C# but using it from other .NET languages should be simple.
</para>
<para>
As it is more of an automation framework than an actual testing framework, you will also need your favourite testing framework
such as <ulink url="http://www.nunit.org/">NUnit</ulink> in order to write tests.
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - A simple example-->
<section>
<title>A simple example</title>
<para>
The key element in IETest is the IEDriver class. It wraps IE automation functionality and supplies help for various common tasks.
The following piece of code will create a new IEDriver which will open Internet Explorer and navigate to Google. Then, it will find the
query input box which has the name "q", and enter "BestBrains" in there. 
Finally, it will locate the search button, named "btnG", and click it. You should see search results popping up just before Internet Explorer
closes.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
using(IEDriver ie = new IEDriver("http://www.google.com", true))
{
	Input q = ie.MainDocument.FindINPUT("q");
	q.Value = "BestBrains";
	
	InputButton btnG = ie.MainDocument.FindINPUT_BUTTON("btnG");
	btnG.Click();
}
]]>
</programlisting>
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[c]-->
</section>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]:Users Guide-->
<section>
<title>Users Guide</title>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[of]: - Structure of IETest-->
<section>
<title>Structure of IETest</title>
<para>

The primary class in IETest is the IEDriver class.
Instaitiating this class will cause Internet Explorer to open and navigate to the requested site.
From there, you will most likely access the main document through the MainDocument method. This is where all the html is stored.



<!--[c]Contents:-->
<!--[c] - IEDriver-->
<!--[c] - Document-->
<!--[c] - xxx element-->
<!--[c] - xxx collection (generated)-->

</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - Using various tags, etc.-->
<section>
<title>Using the various tags, etc.</title>
<para>
At the time of writing, IETest has wraps for the following HTML tags:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>table</listitem>
<listitem>tr</listitem>
<listitem>td</listitem>
<listitem>span</listitem>
<listitem>div</listitem>
<listitem>input</listitem>
<listitem>img</listitem>
<listitem>form</listitem>
<listitem>frame</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

Most of these have simple Find functions. This means that you can write things like:
FindTABLE(elementId), which will locate the table element with the given id.
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - Wandering around the DOM-->
<section>
<title>Wandering Around the DOM</title>
<para>
Sometimes, you simplky don't have an ID of the element you are looking for. Or multiple elements share the same id.
In such cases, you have two options when you really want to locate an element. You can search for it by some other means than
the id, or you can count your way towards, by traversing the DOM. 
Currently, IETest has no way of performing non-id based searches, but this is definitely a high priority task.
There are however ways to traverse the DOM. Firstly, all elements expose a method called NextSibling. This method will give you
the element that immediately follows the current. The Parent() method will give you the element that contains the current.
Furthermore, a number of properties give you a way of locating a child of the current element. TBODY, for instance, will give
you a collection of TableSection's. 
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - Controlling Popup's-->
<section>
<title>Controlling Popup's</title>
<para>
Popups are difficult to test for a number of reasons. Most of all, the IE automation model makes it hard. As far as we can tell, there is no way to 
access the DOM of a modal IE popup.
Therefore, there are some things that simply aren't possible to test. However, if you have access to the code of the web application, 
changing modal dialogs to modeless dialogs can help out in many situations. There are two problems with this approach: firstly, the modeless 
dialog doesn't return a result but instead, it returns a handle to the opened window.
This can be solved with some JavaScript workarounds. The second problem is that focus is not restricted to the dialog - you can click on the 
window behind it and continue doing things even though there is a dialog waiting for input. This is actually not a big problem because for testing 
purposes, you simply won't do that - there should be no user anyway.

Controlling modeless dialogs with IETest is simple. Call IEDriver.GetPopupDocument and you have the document object of your popup. 
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - Alert's-->
<section>
<title>Alert's</title>
<para>
The JavaScript function alert() is quite handy for the web developer. It provides a simple way to give feedback to the user that a form is not filled correctly etc.
Often, these alert messages will be essential to what you are testing. Testing a validation function requires being able to know that it found the data invalid.
IETest offers a way of testing this. The PopupWatcher is a thread that sits in the background looking for alert windows. When one is encountered, it is stored
in a queue. When an alert is expected, call the PopAlert() function which will return a string containing the first popup message that was caught and remove
it from the queue.
When the PopupWatcher is disposed of (usually together with the disposal of IEDriver), it will complain if there were any messages left in the queue, indicating
that an unexpected popup appeared at some point.
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - Threading Apartment-->
<section>
<title>Threading Apartment</title>
<para>
As mshtml expects the host to be running as STA - single threaded apartment - you need to make sure your tests are as well.
If you're using testdriven.net, you won't have a problem but NUnit-gui runs as MTA per default. Hence, you need to change
the threading apartment manually.
The self test illustrates how to do this in your TestFixtureSetUp method:
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
[TestFixtureSetUp]
public void Setup()
{
	System.Threading.Thread.CurrentThread.ApartmentState = System.Threading.ApartmentState.STA;
	
}
]]>
</programlisting>

</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[c]-->
</section>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]:For developers-->
<section>
<title>For Developers</title>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[of]: - Design philosophy-->
<section>
<title>Design philosophy</title>
<para>
IETest was made primarily as an abstraction layer for specialised libraries for testing specific web applications.
Hence, classes have been designed to be overridden.
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]: - Known Issues and Todo's-->
<section>
<title>Known Issues and Todo's</title>
<para>
Todo:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Modal dialogs are not handled. This may or may not be possible at all. Some reseach is required.</listitem>
<listitem>
IEDriver should be able to tell when Javascript is done. Note that this might never happen and that the situation for IETest is identical
to the one of the user. Should you start navigating around a site that is still processing Javscript, you might experience strange behaviour.
</listitem>
<listitem>Collections are being generated by a C# program. Using C# 2.0, this could easily be done with generics.</listitem>
<listitem>Posibility to expose C# classes and functions to Javascript.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</section>
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[c]-->
</section>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[of]:Changelog-->
<section>
<title>Changelog</title>
<para>
0.2 - May 30 2005:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Code generation makefile now only rebuilds if necessary</listitem>
<listitem>Search for tag by text added</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

0.15 - May 30 2005:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Fixed threading apartment in self test. Now runs in NUnit-gui as well.</listitem>
<listitem>Changed collections so they don't contain elements of other types. You can now trust that a DivCollection contains only div's.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

0.1 - May 27 2005: 
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Initial release</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</section>
<!--[c]-->
<!--[cf]-->
<!--[c]-->
</book>
